<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">
<head>
	<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="../def.css" title="Style"/>
</head>


<body>
<h1>Formulas</h1>
<p>
 If you want to present mathemathical formulas in your material,
 you can do this in many ways:
</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Images.</strong> You may use a program like Open Office or Microsoft Office.
 Use the Formula editor and make formula objects on a page.
 You can then freeze a screenshot of the page, clip out the formula and save it as an image.
</li>
<li><strong>Images again</strong>You may use one of the many tools, online or offline, that 
produce imgages from LaTex.
</li>
<li><strong>MathML.</strong> You may write MathML code directly in your material.
</li>
<li><strong>Google.</strong> You may write LaTeX code directly in a the src attribute in an img-element
and let Google prepare an image of the formula, See Google Chart Formulas<?_wxt ref id="googlechartformulas"?>.
The robustness of this approach depends of course on the stability of the Google tool.
</li>
<li><strong>LaTex</strong> You may write let WXT convert LaTex to images.
</li>
<li><strong>Open Office</strong> You may make an Open Office document and let 
 WXT extract the formulas as MatML, see <?_wxt xlink id="ODTFormulas"?>.
 </li>
 
 <li>You may use an XML document describing formulas either as LaTex (latex), MathMl (mathml), 
     LaTeX (google) or image (image).
 See <?_wxt xlink id="Formulas"?>.
 </li>
 
  <li>You may define one formula either as matml, latex, google or imagel.
   See <?_wxt xlink id="PIformula"?>.
 </li>

 </ol>
<p>
 The advantages of involving WXT (5,6,7,8) is that you may find and edit your formulas in one (or a limited)
 places and you may produce lists of used formulas, <?_wxt xlink id="PIformulaList"?>
</p>






 <h3>Browsers</h3>
 <p>
 <strong>Note</strong> that browsers haved different capabilities when we get to MathML.
 You should check this out before deciding how to present math to a wider audience.
 </p>
 <p>
 WXT is at the moment aimed as HTML5, which means that generated MatML may not work on all browser.
</p>
 <!--
 <pre class="prettyprint lang"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1 plus MathML 2.0//EN" 
                  "http://www.w3.org/TR/MathML2/dtd/xhtml-math11-f.dtd">
]]>
 </pre>
 <p>
 and should have an extension: <em>.xhml</em>
 </p>
 -->
 
 
 
 <h3>Formula file</h3>
 <p>Sample</p>
 <div>
 <?_wxt importtxt location="../script/formula-sample.xml" lang="lang-xml"?>
 </div>
 <p>Schema for formula files</p>
 <div>
 <?_wxt importtxt location="formula.xsd" lang="lang-xml"?>
 </div>

</body>
</html>
