<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?>
<div> <div class="importwiki">
    <h3> Hunting and diet</h3>
<p>A successful <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generalist_and_specialist_species" title="Generalist and specialist species">generalist</a> <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Predator" title="Predator">predator</a>, the cougar will eat any animal it can catch, from <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Insect" title="Insect">insects</a> to large <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ungulate" title="Ungulate">ungulates</a> (over 500 kg). Like all cats, it is an <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obligate_carnivore" title="Obligate carnivore">obligate carnivore</a>, feeding only on meat. The Mean weight of vertebrate prey (MWVP) was positively correlated (r=0.875) with puma body weight and inversely correlated (r=-0.836) with food niche breadth in all <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Americas" title="The Americas">America</a>. In general, MWVP was lower in areas closer to the Equator.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-diet_2-2"/> Its most important prey species are various deer species, particularly in North America; <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mule_deer" title="Mule deer">mule deer</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White-tailed_deer" title="White-tailed deer">white-tailed deer</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elk" title="Elk">elk</a>, and even large <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moose" title="Moose">moose</a> are taken by the cat. Other species such as Bighorn Sheep, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mustang_(horse)" title="Mustang (horse)">wild horses of Arizona</a>, domestic horses, and domestic livestock such as cattle and sheep are also primary food bases in many areas.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-SW_29-0"/> A survey of North America research found 68% of prey items were ungulates, especially deer. Only the Florida Panther showed variation, often preferring feral <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hog_(swine)" title="Hog (swine)">hogs</a> and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armadillo" title="Armadillo">armadillos</a>.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-diet_2-3"/>
    </p>
<div class="thumb tright">
<div class="thumbinner">
        <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Mountain_Lion441.jpg">
          <img alt="" class="thumbimage" height="113" src="wikiback/en_wikipedia_org_wiki_Cougar/__Hunting_and_diet/180px_Mountain_Lion441.jpg" width="180"/>
        </a>
<div class="thumbcaption">
<div class="magnify">
            <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Mountain_Lion441.jpg" title="Enlarge">
              <img alt="" height="11" src="wikiback/en_wikipedia_org_wiki_Cougar/__Hunting_and_diet/magnify_clip.png" width="15"/>
            </a>
          </div>
Shown eating. Cougars are ambush predators, feeding mostly on deer and other mammals.</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Investigation in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yellowstone_National_Park" title="Yellowstone National Park">Yellowstone National Park</a> showed that elk, followed by mule deer, were the cougar's primary targets; the prey base is shared with the park's <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gray_Wolf" title="Gray Wolf">gray wolves</a>, with whom the cougar competes for resources.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-Yellowstone_30-0"/> Another study on winter kills (November–April) in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alberta" title="Alberta">Alberta</a> showed that ungulates accounted for greater than 99% of the cougar diet. Learned, individual prey recognition was observed, as some cougars rarely killed <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bighorn_sheep" title="Bighorn sheep">bighorn sheep</a>, while others relied heavily on the species.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-31"/>
    </p>
<p>In the Central and South American cougar range, the ratio of deer in the diet declines. Small to mid-size mammals are preferred, including large rodents such as the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capybara" title="Capybara">capybara</a>. Ungulates accounted for only 35% of prey items in one survey, approximately half that of North America. Competition with the larger jaguar has been suggested for the decline in the size of prey items.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-diet_2-4"/> Other listed prey species of the cougar include <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mice" title="Mice">mice</a>, <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porcupine" title="Porcupine">porcupine</a>, and <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hare" title="Hare">hares</a>. Birds and small reptiles are sometimes preyed upon in the south, but this is rarely recorded in North America.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-diet_2-5"/>
    </p>
<p>Though capable of sprinting, the cougar is typically an <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambush_predator" title="Ambush predator">ambush predator</a>. It stalks through brush and trees, across ledges, or other covered spots, before delivering a powerful leap onto the back of its prey and a suffocating neck bite. The cougar is capable of breaking the neck of some of its smaller prey with a strong bite and momentum bearing the animal to the ground.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-WhosWho_21-1"/>
    </p>
<p>Kills are generally estimated at around one large ungulate every two weeks. The period shrinks for females raising young, and may be as short as one kill every three days when cubs are nearly mature at around 15 months.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-CAP_18-3"/> The cat drags a kill to a preferred spot, covers it with brush, and returns to feed over a period of days. It is generally reported that the cougar is a non-<a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scavenger" title="Scavenger">scavenger</a> and will rarely consume prey it has not killed; but deer carcasses left exposed for study were scavenged by cougars in California, suggesting more opportunistic behavior.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-32"/>
    </p>
</div>
</div>
