<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?>
<div> <div class="importwiki">
    <h3> Subspecies</h3>
<p>Until the late 1990s, as many as 32 <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subspecies" title="Subspecies">subspecies</a> were recorded; however, a recent <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetics" title="Genetics">genetic</a> study of <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitochondrial_DNA" title="Mitochondrial DNA">mitochondrial DNA</a>
      <sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-Culver_12-3"/> found that many of these are too similar to be recognized as distinct at a molecular level. Following the research, the canonical <i>
        <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mammal_Species_of_the_World" title="Mammal Species of the World">Mammal Species of the World</a>
      </i> (3rd edition) recognizes six subspecies, five of which are solely found in <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_America" title="Latin America">Latin America</a>:<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-MSW3_0-2"/>
    </p>
<dl>
<dt>Argentine puma <span>(<i>Puma concolor cabrerae</i>)</span> </dt>
<dd>includes the previous subspecies and synonyms <i>hudsonii</i> and <i>puma</i> (Marcelli, 1922);</dd>
<dt>
        <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Costa_Rican_Cougar" title="Costa Rican Cougar">Costa Rican Cougar</a> <span>(<i>Puma concolor costaricensis</i>)</span>
      </dt>
<dt>Eastern South American cougar <span>(<i>Puma concolor anthonyi</i>)</span> </dt>
<dd>includes the previous subspecies and synonyms <i>acrocodia</i>, <i>borbensis</i>, <i>capricornensis</i>, <i>concolor</i> (Pelzeln, 1883), <i>greeni</i> and <i>nigra</i>;</dd>
<dt>
        <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_American_Cougar" title="North American Cougar">North American Cougar</a> <span>(<i>Puma concolor couguar</i>)</span> </dt>
<dd>includes the previous subspecies and synonyms <i>arundivaga</i>, <i>aztecus</i>, <i>browni</i>, <i>californica</i>, <i>coryi</i>, <i>floridana</i>, <i>hippolestes</i>, <i>improcera</i>, <i>kaibabensis</i>, <i>mayensis</i>, <i>missoulensis</i>, <i>olympus</i>, <i>oregonensis</i>, <i>schorgeri</i>, <i>stanleyana</i>, <i>vancouverensis</i> and <i>youngi</i>;</dd>
<dt>Northern South American cougar <span>(<i>Puma concolor concolor</i>)</span> </dt>
<dd>includes the previous subspecies and synonyms <i>bangsi</i>, <i>incarum</i>, <i>osgoodi</i>, <i>soasoaranna, sussuarana</i>, <i>soderstromii</i>, <i>sucuacuara</i> and <i>wavula</i>;</dd>
<dt>Southern South American puma <span>(<i>Puma concolor puma</i>)</span> </dt>
<dd>includes the previous subspecies and synonyms <i>araucanus</i>, <i>concolor</i> (Gay, 1847), <i>patagonica</i>, <i>pearsoni</i> and <i>puma</i> (Trouessart, 1904)</dd>
</dl>
<p>The status of the <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florida_panther" title="Florida panther">Florida panther</a>, here collapsed into the North American Cougar, remains uncertain. It is still regularly listed as subspecies <i>Puma concolor coryi</i> in research works, including those directly concerned with its conservation.<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-improving_14-0"/> Culver <i>et al.</i> themselves noted low <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsatellite" title="Microsatellite">microsatellite</a> variation in the Florida panther, possibly due to <a class="external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inbreeding" title="Inbreeding">inbreeding</a>;<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-Culver_12-4"/> responding to the research, one conservation team suggests "the degree to which the scientific community has accepted the results of Culver <i>et al.</i> and the proposed change in taxonomy is not resolved at this time."<sup class="reference" id="cite_ref-FloridaRecovery_15-0"/>
    </p>
</div>
</div>
