<!DOCTYPE HTML>
<html lang="en">
<head>
	<meta charset="UTF-8"/>	
    <title><?_wxt fragment id="_name"?></title>
	<link rel="STYLESHEET" href="../commons/frontstyle.css"/>
 	<!--<link rel="STYLESHEET" href="../commons/helpstyle.css"/>-->
    <?_wxt fragment id="resources"?>
</head>
<body>

<?_wxt fragment id="banner"?>

	<div id="topselections">
     <span class="wxtmodulemap">
        <span class="level1"><a href="../index.html" title="Project">Project</a></span> | 
        <span class="level1"><a href="wxt.html" title="Wxt">WXT</a></span> | 
        <span class="level1">Basics</span> | 
        <span class="level1"><a href="download.html" title="download page">Download</a></span> | 
        <span class="level1"> <a href="documentation.html" title="Documentation">Documentation</a></span> | 
        <span class="level1"><a href="samples.html" title="samples page">Samples</a></span>
      </span>


    </div>

<div class="maincontent">


	<h1>Basics</h1>
	<div>[ <?_wxt moduletoc tags="h3" divider="] [" cols="0"?> ]</div>
	<p>
	WXT is based on two concepts: 
	</p>
	<ul>
	<li>a <em>script</em> that describes the structure and the modules we want to build.
	</li>
	<li>the interpretation of <em>Processing Instructions</em> (PI) which are standard XML-nodes. 
	</li>
	</ul>
	<p>Both are explained in detail in 
	<?_wxt xlink id="Documentation"?>.
	</p>
	<h3>The script</h3>
	<div style="float:left;margin:7px"><img  src="structure1.png" alt=""/></div>
	<p>
	The functionality of WXT is based on a script, which is a XML-file. The basic concept is a module.
	A module is described by a template and any number of sources. The sources may be 
	XML, Database, XHTML, Text, HTML(5).
	HTML-content that are not well formed and out of the authors control(typically Wiki) may be tidied on the fly.
	The template must always be a XML or XHTML file.
	</p>
	<p>
	One of the key-concepts in this kind of module building is addressing. WXT recalculates
	references in fragments that are moved.
	</p>
	<p>
	Although the main focus in WXT is on XML-structures, you can also use plain text as content.
	Typically you can import program code snippets an get them color coded as HTML on your module.
	</p>
	<div style="float:right;margin:7px"><img  src="structure2.png" alt=""/></div>
	<p>
	Since the main target of WXT is to share material on the web (or on paper) a lot of
	the concepts in WXT is (X)HTML oriented. You may however use the basic building 
	mechanisms in WXT to produce any kind of XML, or text for that matter.
	</p>
	<p>
	One key to this flexibility is the use of XSLT. You may transform content before
	you bring it to the template and you may transform a module before you save it.
	</p>
	
	<h3>Processing Instructions</h3>
	<p>
	The other key concept in WXT is the use of processing instructions.
	A processing instruction (PI) is legal XML in any XML-file. The program that
	parses a XML-file will detect the PI's and may act on them. The format of a PI is 
	like this:
	</p>
	<pre class="source">
&lt;?name data?&gt;
	</pre>
	<p>
	The name and data may have any value. WXT will recognize and react on 
	PI's with name <em>_wxt</em>. The data part is interpreted as a command identifier followed by 
	a series of name, value pairs.
	Just like attributes in a XML-element.
	For instance:
	</p>
	<pre class="source">
&lt;?_wxt importxml location="myfile.xml" xpath="//div[@id='export']"?&gt;
	</pre>
	<p>
	will instruct WXT to extract the div with id="export" from the file myfile.xml and replace the PI with the result.
	The following:
	</p>
	<pre class="source">
&lt;?_wxt modulemap books="math"?&gt;
	</pre>
	<p>
	will instruct WXT to produce links to all modules that are marked with book="math" in the script.
	</p>
	
	<h3>Running WXT</h3>
	<p>
	You can run WXT from the command line with the following syntax (windows):
	</p>
	<pre>
java -jar wxtn.jar script.xml [-m module1[,module2]]
	</pre>
	<p>For instance:
	</p>
	<pre>
java -jar C:\myWxt\dist\wxt6.jar C:\mysite\script.xml 

java -jar C:\myWxt\dist\wxt6.jar C:\mysite\script.xml -m firstpage,lastpage
	</pre>
	<p>
	You may also download the GUI, see <?_wxt xlink id="Download"?>, and control the building in more detail.
	</p>

</div>

    <div id="footer">
    <?_wxt fragment id="footer"?>
    </div>

</body>
</html>
