<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">
<head>
	<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="../def.css" title="Style"/>
</head>

<body>
<h1>PI: imagelist</h1>
<p>
 This PI will present a list of imagethumbs that may be expanded by
 mouseover to show the image. The images must be defined in an images-list, see <?_wxt xlink id="Images"?>,
  or as an image, see <?_wxt xlink id="PIimage"?>. 
</p>
<pre class="piline">
&lt;?_wxt imagelist?&gt;
</pre>


<p>The parameters are:</p>
<table cellpadding="10px">
  
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>thumbsize</strong> (removed)</td>
    <td>Defining the height of the thumbs, default is 100px.
	   This parameter must be set in the stylesheet.
     </td>
  </tr>
 
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>split</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>Will insert a break before the thumbs for a new  module. 
	Possible values are <em>yes</em> and <em>no</em>. <em>no</em> is default.
     </td>
  </tr> 
  
	<tr>
	<td> </td>
	<td>
	The parameters below is to select the modules we want to select images from.
	Description below.
	</td>
	</tr>
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>idlist</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>A commaseparated list of module ids that we want to include.
      If this is set, the others (select, root and books) are ignored.
     </td>
  </tr>
    <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>scriptpath</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>The scriptpath is an xpath that is used on the script to select modules.<br/>
       Sample: //module[@template='P'] get all modules with template P.    
     </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>root</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>The id of the module that defines the subtree we will make a map for.
     </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>books</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>A commaseparated list of book ids that we want to include.
     </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>select</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>Possible values are _siblings and _children.
    
     </td>
  </tr>

  </table>
  
  <p class="stylefoot">
Styleclass describing this PI is: <em>wxtthumbwrapper</em> and <em>wxtimagelist</em>.
A popping image is identified and styled as <em>wxt-img-popup</em>, see distributed std styles.
</p>
  
  
<p>
    The selected set of modules will be assembled according to the following rule:
</p>
<ul>
    <li>if <em>idlist</em> is set, the collection is as defined in the idlist.</li>
    <li>if <em>idlist</em> is not set, the collection is made up as the intersection
        of the modules spesified by <em>root</em>, <em>book</em>, <em>scriptpath</em> and <em>select</em>.</li>
    <li>if neither <em>idlist</em>, <em>root</em>, <em>book</em>, <em>scriptpath</em> or <em>select</em> is set, 
	all modules are selected, except those with books attribute: <em>_never</em>.</li>
</ul>



</body>
</html>
