<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">
<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="../def.css" title="Style"/>
</head>


<body>
<h1>PI: importodf</h1>
<p>
  The purpose of an importodf PI is to produce an XML-fragment 
  from extracts from an Open Office document and replace the PI with this fragment. 
</p>
<p>
<strong>NOTE:</strong> That the form of this PI may change.
Specially the use of <em>dpath</em>, and the form of the dpath may be changed.
It is present at an experimental stage. 
</p>
<pre class="piline">
&lt;?_wxt importodf dpath="" location=""?&gt;
</pre>
<p>
 This import is not complete in the sense that it handles all kinds of objects that
 may be placed in an Open Office document. WXT can identify: headings, text paragraphs, 
 images, formulas (math), lists and tables.
</p>
<p>
 WXT apply a strategy that backs up the latest
 successfull import, and use this if an import fails. The backup strategy does not
 consider changes in content, but if your <em>dpath</em>, se below, fails to
 identify any material at all, the backup is used. More about <?_wxt xlink id="DPath"?>.
</p>
<p>
 This backup strategy cost processing time. You may change the strategy by parameters
 backup and usecopy, see below.
</p>



<p>The parameters are:</p>
<table cellpadding="10px">
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>dpath</strong> mandatory</td>
    <td>The content of any header(h1, h2,.., h6) in the wikipage.
    Content will be extracted until we meet a heading with same or higher
    significance. dpath (documentpath) has the form:
	h1/h2/h3. For instance /Report/summary will extract content in 
	h3:summary "under" h2:report.<br/>
	dpath may also have a predicate part. <br/>
    /Report/summary[p] will collect only paragraphs in the selected part.
	See <?_wxt xlink id="DPath"?>.
    </td>
  </tr>
 <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>xpath</strong> optional</td>
    <td>Defaults to //body.  <br/>   
	Either <em>dpath</em> or <em>xpath</em> must be set. 
	If<em>dpath</em> is set, <em>xpath</em> is ignored
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>location</strong> mandatory</td>
    <td>The location of the file we want to import from.
	In templates the location parameter is usually skipped. 
	In this case all content files (odtimport) owned by the module in the script are searched for 
	appropriate content unless you reduce the search with parameter id, see below. 
     </td>
  </tr>
 <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>usecopy</strong> optional</td>
    <td>Possible values are <em>yes</em> and <em>no</em>.
	<em>yes</em> will load the local backup without attempting to 
	load the source. This will save time, but it does of course only have meaning
	if you have accessed and loaded the material at least once before.
	Default is <em>no</em>. This setting will be overridden by the option <em>use-copy</em>,
	see <?_wxt xlink id="Options"?>
     </td>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>id</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>An id that match the id of the actual xmlimport 
    in script. Has only meaning when
    this element has no location. One reason to use an id is 
    processing time if you have many contentfiles to a module.
	Another reason may be that you have similar structures in different contentfiles and you
	want to be selective.
    </td>
  </tr>

  
  </table>

<p>
    <strong>NOTE: </strong>
    WXT does not consider styles, most elements are copied "as is".
</p>


<h2>Examples:</h2>
<pre class="source">
&lt;?_wxt importodf 
         location="doc1.odf" 
         dpath="/Illustrations"?&gt;
</pre>
<p>
 will extract the header on level 2, Illustrations, and all
 material until the next heading at level 2, or level1.
</p>



</body>
</html>
