<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">
<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="../def.css" title="Style"/>
</head>


<body>
<h1>PI: importhtml</h1>
<p>
  The purpose of an importhtml PI is to produce a wellformed HTML-fragment 
  and replace the PI with this fragment.
  WXT may attempt to do a simple tiding with jsoup <?_wxt ref id="jsoup"?> if parsing of the HTML-material fails.
  Note however that even if the tidy job is successfull the result may no be exactly as you expect.
</p>
<p>
 There are basically to forms of html-import, depending on the parameter <em>remote</em>, see below.
</p>
<p>
You should use importhtml in stead of importxml if you want to apply a cssselector,
all though it is possible to use a xpath even in importhml if you do not set the remote-parameter.
The css selection is also withjsoup<?_wxt ref id="jsoup"?>.
</p>
<pre class="piline">
&lt;?_wxt importhtml cssselector="" location=""?&gt;
</pre>

<p>The parameters are:</p>
<table cellpadding="10px">
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>location</strong> mandatory, but optional in templates</td>
    <td>The URI of the file we want to import from. WXT will if necessary 
	    attempt to tidy the source.
		<br/>
        In templates the location parameter is usually skipped.
        In this case all content files owned by the module in the script are 
        searched for appropriate content unless you reduce 
		the search with parameter <em>id</em>, see below.
     </td>
  </tr>
   <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>encoding</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>You can spesify expected encoding if you expect the import
	to be without XML-header stating the encoding.
	Default encoding is UTF-8 if not set otherwise in script (option: default-encoding).
    </td>
  </tr>   
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>id</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>An id that match the id of the actual xmlimport 
    in script. Has only meaning when
    this element has no location. One reason to use an id is 
    processing time if you have many contentfiles to a module.
	Another reason may be that you have similar structures in different contentfiles and you
	want to be selective.
    </td>
  </tr>  
  
    <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>keeplinks</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>May be <em>yes</em> or <em>no</em>. If <em>yes</em>,
          wxt will attempt to recalculate all links in the imported html. 
		  If <em>no</em> all links are removed.
		  Default is <em>yes</em>
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>keepstyles</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>May be <em>yes</em> or <em>no</em>. If <em>no</em>,
          wxt will simply remove all class- and style-attributes from HTML-tags.
		  Default is <em>yes</em>.
    </td>
  </tr> 
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>xpath</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>Any xpath expression that identifies a nodeset that
        will be treated like a XML-fragment.
		</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>cssselector</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>A cssselector that identifies a nodeset that
        will be treated like a HTML-fragment. If neither <em>xpath</em> nor <em>cssselector</em> is set
		the selection defaults to cssselector="body p".
		</td>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
  <td colspan="2">If both are set ,xpath is used, unless we spesify remote (see below).
  </td>
  </tr>
  
  
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>remote</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>Should be used if we try to import from a webpage over wich we have no control
	( for instance a wikipedia-page). 
	<br/>
	If we use <em>remote</em> <span style="color:red">xpath is ignored</span>.
    </td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>usecopy</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>May be <em>yes</em> or <em>no</em>, and is only effective for <em>remote</em>
	sources. Default is <em>yes</em>.
	<br/>
	<em>no</em> will access the material at the original source, 
	produce a local copy and then fetch the result from this copy.
	This parameter will be overrun by global option <em>use-copy</em>.
    </td>
  </tr>

</table>
<p>
</p>

<h2>Examples:</h2>
<pre  class="prettyprint lang-html">
&lt;?_wxt importhtml xpath="//h1"?&gt;

&lt;?_wxt importhtml location="http://no.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halden" 
             cssselector="body > p" remote="yes" keeplinks="no"?&gt;

&lt;?_wxt importhtml 
        location="http://www.ia.hiof.no/~borres/ml/index.shtml" 
        xpath="//div[@class='main']/*"?&gt;

&lt;?_wxt importhtml location="../quotes/q.xml" 
        xpath="//p[@class='quot']/*"?&gt;

		
&lt;?_wxt importhtml location="C:\\web\\dw\\index.html" 
       cssselector="article"?&gt;

</pre>



</body>
</html>
