<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en">
<head>
  <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="../def.css" title="Style"/>
</head>


<body>
<h1>PI: importwiki</h1>
<p>
  The purpose of an importwiki PI is to produce an XML-fragment 
  from extracts from a wiki-page and replace the PI with this fragment. 
</p>
<p>
<strong>NOTE:</strong> That the form of this PI may change.
Specially the use of <em>dpath</em>, and the form of the dpath may be changed.
It is present at an experimental stage.
</p>
<pre class="piline">
&lt;?_wxt importwiki dpath="" location=""?&gt;
</pre>
<p>
 As wikipages by their nature are changing, WXT apply a strategy that backs up the latest
 successfull import, and use this if an import fails. The backup strategy does not
 consider changes in content, but if your <em>dpath</em> or <em>xpath</em>, se below, fails to
 identify any material at all, the backup is used. More about <?_wxt xlink id="DPath"?> 
 and <?_wxt xlink id="XPath"?>.
</p>
<p>
 This backup strategy cost processing time. You may change the strategy by parameter
 usecopy, see below.
</p>


<p>The parameters are:</p>
<table cellpadding="10px">
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>dpath</strong> optional</td>
    <td>The content of any header(h1, h2,.., h6) in the wikipage.
    Content will be extracted until we meet a heading with same or higher
    significance. dpath (documentpath) has the form:
	h1/h2/h3. For instance /Report/summary will extract content in 
	h3:summary "under" h2:report.<br/>
    Either <em>dpath</em> or <em>xpath</em> must be set. 
	If<em>dpath</em> is set, <em>xpath</em> is ignored.
    dpath may also have a specification part. <br/>
    /Report/summary[p] will collect only paragraphs in the selected part.
	See <?_wxt xlink id="DPath"?>.
	</td>
  </tr>
 <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>xpath</strong> optional</td>
    <td>Defaults to //body.  <br/>   
	Either <em>dpath</em> or <em>xpath</em> must be set. 
	If<em>dpath</em> is set, <em>xpath</em> is ignored
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>location</strong> mandatory</td>
    <td>The URI of the file we want to import from.
	In templates the location parameter is usually skipped.
        In this case all content files (wikicontent) listed in the script
        as direct children of the module are 
        searched for appropriate content.
        You can reduce the search with parameter <em>id</em>, see below.
     </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>keeprefs</strong> optional</td>
    <td>Possible values ar: <em>yes</em> and <em>no</em>. If <em>yes</em>
    all references in the imported material is recalculated and kept.
    If <em>no</em> all references are removed.
    <em>no</em> is default.
     </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>encoding</strong> optional</td>
    <td>You can spesify expected encoding.
    Default encoding is default (UTF-8 if not set otherwise in script).
     </td>
  </tr>
 <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>backup</strong> optional</td>
    <td>You may spesify the catalog you want to use for backup.
	Default is catalog <em>wikibck</em> in the same catalog as the module requesting the material.
	You may also use the value <em>no</em> to suppress the backup strategy.
     </td>
  </tr>
 <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>usecopy</strong> optional</td>
    <td>Possible values are <em>yes</em> and <em>no</em>.
	<em>yes</em> will load the backup without attempting to 
	load the wiki-page. This will save time, but it does of course only have meaning
	if you have accessed and loaded the material at least once before.
	Default is <em>no</em>. This setting will be overridden by the option <em>use-copy</em>,
	see <?_wxt xlink id="Options"?>
     </td>
  </tr>
  
  <tr>
    <td  style="vertical-align:top"><strong>id</strong> (optional)</td>
    <td>An id that match the id of the actual xmlimport 
    in script. Has only meaning when
    this element has no location. One reason to use an id is 
    processing time if you have many contentfiles to a module.
	Another reason may be that you have similar structures in different contentfiles and you
	want to be selective.
    </td>
  </tr>

  
  </table>

<p>
    <strong>NOTE 1: </strong>
    WXT does not consider styles, most elements are copied "as is".
</p>
<p>
    <strong>NOTE 2: </strong>
    WXT is not set up to collect from https (Secure connentions). If you want to 
    access protected files, you should use normal access through a webbrowser and save the
    page on your disk. Then you can access the downloaded file locally.
</p>
<p>
    <strong>NOTE 3: </strong>
    The backup strategy makes it possible to inspect and even change the
	downloaded content.
</p>
<p>
    <strong>NOTE 4: </strong>
    In many cases you can achive your result by importing the wikipage by importxml and a xpath.
	WXT will attempt to tidy the import.
</p>
<h2>Examples:</h2>
<pre class="source">
&lt;?_wxt importwiki 
         location="mycopiedwikifile.html" 
         dpath="/All students"?&gt;
</pre>
<p>
 will extract the header on level 2, All students, and all
 material until the next heading at level 2, or level1.
</p>
<pre class="source">
&lt;?_wxt importwiki  keeprefs="no" 
       location="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cougar" 
	   dpath="//Subspecies"?&gt;
</pre>
<p>
 will extract a description of Subspecies (placed at header level3)
 in a wikipedia - page about cougars.
</p>
<pre class="source">
&lt;?_wxt importwiki dpath="/Nature" 
     location="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halden"?&gt;
</pre>
<p>
will produce this (as of june 2009)
</p>
<pre class="result">
&lt;div class="importwiki"&gt;&lt;h2&gt; Nature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Halden is surrounded by forests and water so hiking and fishing
locations can easily be found. Deer and elk are a common sight, 
and wolves have also been observed
in the district along the border with Sweden. 
Raspberries, blackberries, blueberries, wild cranberries, and many 
varieties of mushroom can be found in
the woods in the early autumn. Popular destinations for hikers and
other nature lovers include Prestebakke and Kornsjø.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</pre>


</body>
</html>
