<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1 plus MathML 2.0//EN"
               "http://www.w3.org/TR/MathML2/dtd/xhtml-math11-f.dtd" 
[
  <!ENTITY mathml "http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
]>  
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
	<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8"></meta>
	<OBJECT ID="mathplayer" CLASSID="clsid:32F66A20-7614-11D4-BD11-00104BD3F987"> 
	<!--comment required to prevent this becoming an empty tag--></OBJECT>
	<?IMPORT NAMESPACE="m" IMPLEMENTATION="#mathplayer" ?>

	<title><?_wxt fragment id="_name"?></title>
	<?_wxt fragment id="styles_and_scripts"?>
</head>
<body>
	<div>
	<?_wxt fragment id="banner"?>
	</div>
	<table class="mainpage">
	<tr>

	<td valign="top" width="120px">
		<?_wxt modulemenu summary="no"?>
	</td>

	<td valign="top">
		<h1>Introduction</h1>
		<p>
		Describing the Bezier function.
		</p>
		<hr/>
		<!--[if IE]>
		<p>Make sure you have installed mathPlayer.
		Test (and install) at: <a href="http://www.dessci.com/en/products/mathplayer/check.htm">www.dessci.com/en/products/mathplayer/check.htm</a></p>
		<hr/>
		<![endif]-->

		<p>
		This is a demonstration of a some document manipulation.
		The basic source is the file Bezier.odt. 
		The link is here:<a href="Bezier.odt">Bezier.odt</a>. If you have Open Office installed, there
		is a chance your browser will reckognize it and suggest that it is opened in Open Office Document Writer.
		</p>
		<p>
		I do the following experiments with this file, Bezier.odt.
		</p>
		<ol>
		<li>I export the file from Open Office as xhtml, see <a href="direct/BezierAuto.xhtml">BezierAuto.xhtml</a>
		</li>
		<li>I save the file from Open Office as pdf, see <a href="direct/BezierAuto.pdf">BezierAuto.pdf</a>
		</li>
		<li>I use WXT to extract pieces from the file, add some stuff, and build a web site,
		see link Bezier in left menu. I also let WXT collect from the website, 
		<a href="collected.xhtml">collected.xhtml</a>
		and I let WXT apply <a href="http://www.princexml.com/">Prince</a> to  build PDF<a href="collected.pdf">collected.pdf</a>.
				<hr/>
		<div>
		The script for this site is like this:
		</div>
		<div>
		<?_wxt expand sourcelocation="script.xml" location="scriptsrc.txt" code="xmlcode"?>
		</div>
		<hr/>
		</li>
		</ol>

		<p>I also add a few applets to the web modules, and I have written some stuff in HTML in an accessible editor,
		like Notepad++ or Adobe Dreamweaver.
		The applets are directly accessible from the net.
		</p>
		<p>
		The quoted C-code in module <?_wxt xlink id="5 OpenGL"?> would in a normal situation be fetched from the actual programproject. 
		Here it is simply pasted into the page, 
		</p>
		<p>
		Please note that this is neither a demonstration of pedagogy nor mathematics, it is just a demonstration of
		some of the features in WXT.
		</p>
		<p>
		Do also note there are some restrictions on WXT's ability to handle OO-format. Essentially it is restricted to
		headers, paragraphs, tables, images, formulas and lists. WXT does not replicate styling.
		</p>

	</td>
   
	</tr>
	</table>
	<div><?_wxt fragment id="footer"?></div>
</body>
</html>